This means we will realize that the eye, ultimately, presents us with a profound illusion.
つまり、最終的に目は私たちに巨大な幻想を与えていることに気づくでしょう。
For example, you have the impression that I exist here before you.
例えば、あなたは私がここにあなたの前に存在していると感じています。
You truly have this impression.
あなたは本当にそう感じています。
In fact, I am a mirage.
実際、私は蜃気楼です。
From time to time, I will disappear like this.
私は時々、このように消えてしまいます。
So, and especially, thank you to Dominique for this invitation
そして、この招待をしてくれたドミニクに特に感謝します。
to present this work.
この作品を発表するために。
So the idea here will also be,
ですから、ここでのアイデアは、
well, you are somewhat familiar with all the sanitary conditions,
まあ、あなたはすべての衛生状態を少し知っています。
I believe everyone must be responsible for themselves,
私は誰もが自分自身に責任を持つべきだと思います。
knowing what to do and what not to do.
何をすべきか、何をすべきでないかを知ること。
I invite you, especially, in this context here,
私はあなたに、特にこの状況で、
is to wash your hands, in fact, frequently.
頻繁に手を洗うことです。
I believe that's where much occurs,
それが多くの場所で起こっていると思います。
especially since we will still be touching the body somewhat.
特に私たちはまだ少し体に触れるからです。
We won't be undressing, but we will still be touching the body.
服を脱ぐわけではありませんが、それでも体に触れます。
So the only thing I propose to you,
ですから、私が提案する唯一のことは、
is to be attentive, to wash your hands thoroughly.
注意深く、よく手を洗うことです。
and then if you have minor symptoms
そして、もしあなたが少し症状があるなら、
or things like that, you keep your mask on
またはそのようなものがあるなら、マスクを着用してください。
but the most important thing
しかし、最も重要なことは、
will still be hand washing
やはり手洗いでしょう。
there was a study conducted
ある研究が行われました。
where transmission was reduced by 98%
それによると、手だけで感染が98%減少しました。
solely through hand hygiene, in large-scale settings.
大規模な状況で、手だけで。
therefore
ですから、
this is my only suggestion
それが私の唯一の提案です。
and I invite you to be responsible
そして、私はあなたに責任を持つことを提案します。
for each of you
一人ひとりが。
what is your name?
お名前は何ですか？
Anne-Marie
アンヌ＝マリー
we don't know each other yet
まだ知り合いではありません。
Anne-Marie, I think
アンヌ＝マリーだと思います。
Some new faces here, some people I already know.
新しい人もいれば、すでに知っている人もいます。
So, hello everyone, I hope you are all doing well too.
皆さん、こんにちは。皆さんもお元気であることを願っています。
So, here we are, we will actually explore some considerations,
では、いくつかの考察を見ていきましょう。
which I hope will enable you, assist you in your practice,
それがあなたの実践、あなたの研究に役立つことを願っています。
in your research.
あなたの研究に役立つことを願っています。
In this quest for osteopathy, both on a
この研究は、オステオパシーの純粋に構造的、機能的な側面だけでなく、
purely structural, functional level, but also on a level...
純粋に構造的、機能的な側面だけでなく、ある側面についてもです。
perhaps a little more of a spiritual nature.
おそらく、もう少し精神的な秩序があるかもしれません。
I believe osteopathy can nonetheless lead us to a concept,
オステオパシーは、私たちをある概念、
to an elevation of each individual.
個人の高揚へと導くことができると私は思います。
And I am thinking in particular of an American woman named Johanna
特に、ジョアンナというアメリカ人女性のことを考えています。
Messi.
メッシ。
Johanna Messi, she wrote a book,
ジョアンナ・メッシは本を書きました。
and just the title of this book, I didn't even need to read it.
その本のタイトルだけで、読む必要はありませんでした。
The title alone was enough to give me a kind of...
そのタイトルだけで、私に一種の…
of revelation, an awareness as well.
啓示、意識を与えてくれました。
The book is 'The Earth, the Planet, as'
その本は、「地球、惑星を、
'Self'.
自分自身として」というものです。
This perhaps means that we have a way of being ourselves,
それは、おそらく私たちは自分自身である方法を持っているということ、
a vision we hold, and in fact, we have a very restricted view of ourselves.
私たちが持っているビジョン、そして実際には自分自身に対して非常に限定されたビジョンを持っているということです。
And perhaps we could consider ourselves, for these few days already,
そして、おそらく私たちは、この数日間だけでも、
and perhaps beyond.
そしておそらくそれ以上、自分自身を考えることができるでしょう。
In any case, it's something I'm increasingly paying attention to, which is
いずれにせよ、私はますますこのことに注意を払うようになっています。それは、
to consider the Earth perhaps as myself, not in a literal sense, you see, but rather within a notion
地球を自分自身として考えることです。ある意味で、あなたは理解していますが、むしろ
of respect.
尊敬の念からです。
And then to consider the Earth as a beloved, as my beloved,
そして、地球を愛する人として、私の愛する人として考えることです。
you see.
わかりますか。
Because, ultimately, I
なぜなら、最終的に、私は
will talk to you about what we call aggregates.
「集合体」と呼ばれるものについて話すからです。
Already, this term...
まず、この用語…
You might already not quite know what aggregates are.
集合体とは何か、あなたはまだ知らないかもしれません。
Ultimately, we are a sum of aggregates.
結局のところ、私たちは集合体の総和です。
We are a composition, you see, momentary, impermanent, interdependent,
私たちは、一時的で、無常で、相互依存的な構成体です。
that comes and goes.
来ては去るものです。
And within these aggregates, we speak, among other things, of form, and we speak, among other things, of the earth, you
そして、これらの集合体の中で、私たちはとりわけ形について話し、とりわけ地球について話します。
see.
わかりますか。
And also of the great play of perceptions, because we will work a bit with that.
そして、知覚の大きなゲームについてもです。なぜなら、私たちはそれを使って少し作業するからです。
great play of perceptions. And in this great play of perceptions, ultimately, after
知覚の大きなゲーム。そして、この知覚の大きなゲームの中で、最終的に、
observation,
観察の後、
our perceptions, if we observe them closely, are nothing but like
私たちの知覚は、よく観察すれば、まるで
mirages. In fact, there is something
蜃気楼のようなものです。実際、何か
very blurry, ultimately. We think, because we have fixed things, but
非常に曖昧なものがあります。私たちは、物事を固定したからそう思うのですが、
ultimately, it is still
結局のところ、それはやはり
quite blurry. So, it's this notion of interpretation, this notion of...
かなり曖昧です。したがって、これは解釈の概念、この概念です…
how we see things, how we see the things around us. And so the game that
私たちは物事をどのように見ているか、私たちの周りの物事をどのように見ているか。そして、構築されたゲームは、
has been constructed, ultimately, is also an interpretation,
結局のところ、これも解釈であり、
an interpretation of
解釈です。
things, of phenomena. Ultimately, we are a phenomenology. So
物、現象。結局のところ、私たちは女性学です。だから
the idea is
その考えは
perhaps we could somewhat change this mode of perception, go
おそらく、この知覚のモードを少し変えて、
perhaps into
おそらく、
another mirage, perhaps a slightly larger mirage, perhaps as large as the
別の蜃気楼、おそらくもう少し大きな蜃気楼、おそらく
So I think it's interesting to tell ourselves, well, if we have this awareness that we
地球と同じくらい大きな蜃気楼に向かうことができるでしょう。
would be like this planet and if we become truly aware, you see, we would
だから、もし私たちがこの惑星のような意識を持っているとすれば、そして私たちが意識すれば、本当に、私たちはこの惑星をもう少し大切にするようになるでしょう。なぜなら、私たちはまだ現在の状況にいることを知っておく必要があるからです。
perhaps take a little more care of this planet, because we must still know that we
この惑星のような意識を持っているとすれば、そして私たちが意識すれば、本当に、私たちはこの惑星をもう少し大切にするようになるでしょう。なぜなら、私たちはまだ現在の状況にいることを知っておく必要があるからです。
are still in the current context.
おそらくもう少し大切にするでしょう。なぜなら、私たちはまだ現在の状況にいることを知っておく必要があるからです。
est quand même dans le contexte actuel.
現在の状況にいます。
within the current societal context,
社会が置かれている状況の中で、
within this context of climate crisis,
この気候危機の状況の中で、
which is, indeed, of paramount importance.
それは非常に重要なことです。
I believe we do not yet possess adequate awareness of this.
まだ十分に意識されていないと思います。
Indeed, we are, yet it appears somewhat as a mirage, ultimately.
はい、意識はしていますが、結局のところ、蜃気楼のようなものです。
Within this context of social crisis,
この社会危機の状況の中で、
which is also a significant event we are currently traversing.
これもまた、私たちが経験している重要な出来事です。
Within this context...
この文脈で...
also regarding the highly significant phenomenon of immigration,
また、非常に重要になるであろう移民のすべてについて、
fundamentally, we are, I
実際、私たちは、実際、私は
believe we are at a truly pivotal juncture, and
本当に重要な転換点にいると思います。そして、
this is referred to as the Great Turning, you see, and we
私たちはそれを大きな転換点と呼んでいます。ご存知のように、私たちはホムンクルスと呼ばれる社会にいます。
exist within a society, as you are well aware, where we function according to what is termed the 'homo economicus',
経済学的な社会、つまり私たちは
economicus,' meaning we are in a society where we are driven by
成長の社会にいます。しかし実際には、私たちは完全にこの成長のモードで機能しています。
growth. Fundamentally, we operate entirely within this paradigm of growth.
私たちは完全にそれに囚われています。この産業成長、この
We are entirely engrossed in this industrial growth, in this
成長は、結局のところ、世界を無限のものと見なしています。しかし、
growth that ultimately perceives the world as an infinite entity, whereas
私たちは
we
有限の世界にいます。本当の変化があります。そして、もし
exist within a finite world. A profound shift is occurring. And if
私があなたにこれについて話すのは、
I address this topic, it is
私があなたに少し異なる視点を提案したいからです。
because I wish to propose, to invite you to adopt a perspective
なぜなら、私たちは、私たちが呼ぶものに向かっているからです。この転換点を乗り越えるか、
that is somewhat divergent.
いずれにしても崩壊に向かっています。
Because we are progressing towards what
それは、それが創発の理論であるという事実から明らかです。
is termed; either we successfully navigate this turning point, or we
そして、それは常に身体の中に見られる創発の理論になるでしょう。
such, even within the corporeal domain.
身体の中に見られる創発の理論になるでしょう。
It emerges, and subsequently, it collapses.
それは現れては崩壊します。
And the society in which we currently exist is progressing towards...
そして、私たちがいる社会は、私たちは...に向かっています。
this tipping point.
ce point de bascule.
I think that we, as therapists,
Je pense que nous, en tant que thérapeute,
actually have a role
on a un rôle, en fait,
to play. A role
à jouer. Un rôle
to play in perhaps
à jouer de peut-être
bringing our patients
amener nos patients
through this relief of
par ce soulagement de la
suffering that we provide, but also through this notion
souffrance qu'on fait, mais aussi par cette notion
of opening up a bit, you see.
d'un peu s'ouvrir, tu vois.
Andrea Zmessi said, we will need
Andréa Zmessi disait, il nous faudra
three things. Three things to
trois choses. Trois choses pour
perhaps make this turning point.
peut-être faire ce tournant.
The very first thing,
La toute première chose,
is that somehow, we must mobilize a bit nonetheless.
c'est que quelque part, on doit un peu se mobiliser quand même.
There have been movements like this that have occurred,
Il y a eu des mouvements comme ça qui se sont faits,
where we must say, no, it's no.
où on doit dire, mais non, c'est non.
But it's no, not specifically, you see,
Mais c'est non, pas spécialement, tu vois,
it's also no, to oneself, you see, to be in this hyper-system.
c'est aussi non, soi, tu vois, d'être dans cet hyper-système.
It's also, at some point, saying no to oneself.
C'est aussi, à un moment donné, de se dire non.
No, that's enough now, you see.
Non, ça suffit maintenant, tu vois.
I must become aware.
Je dois prendre conscience.
The second important thing,
Deuxième chose qui est importante,
is to create new ideas, new forms.
c'est créer des nouvelles idées, des nouvelles formes.
As I think we will clearly see, in the
Comme  je  pense  qu 'on  verra  bien,  au
end,
bout  du  compte,
that this climate crisis relocates things.
que cette crise climatique relocalise les choses.
Rahman has a new awareness, a new view.
Rahman a une nouvelle conscience, une nouvelle vue.
This is also the view I want to propose to you.
C'est ça aussi la vue que je veux vous proposer.
It's becoming aware of this, this new view.
C'est prendre conscience de ça, cette nouvelle vue.
This notion, it's...
Cette notion-là, c'est...
but it leads us to be creators, to be
mais  ça  nous  amène  à  être  créateur,  à  être
thinkers.
penseur.
And this brings us to a third very important point.
Et ça nous amène à une troisième chose qui est très importante.
We also have, as I mentioned three things, do you remember,
C'est qu'on a aussi, pour que je parle de trois choses, vous vous souvenez,
the first thing was to mobilize a little, but also to mobilize oneself.
la  première  chose,  c 'était  se  mobiliser  un  petit  peu,  mais  se  mobiliser  soi -même  aussi.
The second thing is to find other solutions, to consider other possibilities,
Deuxième  chose,  c 'est  trouver  d 'autres  solutions,  penser  à  d 'autres  possibilités,
other perspectives.
d 'autres  vues.
And the third thing is to undertake spiritual work.
Et troisième chose, c'est faire un travail spirituel.
I believe that if these three conditions, at least, as proposed by Yonah
Je  pense  que  si  ces  trois  conditions,  en  tout  cas,  c 'est  ce  que  propose  Yonah
Messi,
Messi,
if these three conditions are not met, we will not be able to make this shift.
もしこれら3つの条件が満たされなければ、この転換はできません。
We will be limited.
私たちは制限されます。
And this spiritual work, ultimately, is a work
そして、この精神的な仕事は、結局のところ、
that we perform here.
私たちがここで行う仕事です。
It is also a form of spiritual work that we will undertake.
これもまた、私たちが行う精神的な仕事の一形態です。
That is, to develop beautiful consciousness, a good heart,
それは、美しい意識、善良な心を発達させることです。
whether it is, this is not a course on religion, but it is nonetheless a course on a
これは宗教に関するコースではありませんが、それでも
consciousness.
意識に関するコースです。
I believe that at this spiritual level, we are in this elevation.
この精神的なレベルでは、私たちはこの高みにいると思います。
That is, it's about asking ourselves how we can somewhat reduce
つまり、どうすれば苦しみを少しでも減らせるか、という問いを自分に投げかけることです。
suffering as well.
苦しみも。
But not just my own.
しかし、私だけの苦しみではありません。
Not just yours, but perhaps to open up a little, because I
あなただけの苦しみではなく、おそらく少し開くことです。なぜなら、私は
think of Cominada.
コミナーダを考えています。
You know Cominada, he is one of the leaders of Greenpeace.
コミナーダをご存知ですか？彼はグリーンピースのリーダーの一人です。
He said, I believe that you, therapists, you, meditators,
彼は言いました。「セラピストであるあなた方、瞑想するあなた方には、
you have the capacity, without realizing it, to
気づかないうちに、他の人に教える能力があります。」
teach others.
他の人に教える能力があります。
another form of pleasure.
別の形の喜びを。
Because we are constantly seeking pleasure, in fact,
なぜなら、私たちは常に喜びを求めているからです。
of desire, pleasure.
欲望、喜び。
Perhaps we have the capacity,
私たちには能力があるかもしれません。
through our work,
私たちの仕事を通して、
to teach others
他の人に教えること。
the discovery of another form of pleasure.
別の形の喜びを発見することを。
So, for example,
例えば、
because most of the time,
ほとんどの場合、
we are just in the pleasure of our senses.
私たちはただ感覚の喜びに浸っています。
I see, I surprised myself the other day, I was in town and
私は先日、街にいて、自分自身に驚きました。
I was walking and I saw that my whole
散歩していて、私のシステム全体が
system was drawn to seek pleasure; I
私を喜ばせるために引き寄せられているのを見ました。私は
entered a bookstore and I was looking
本屋に入って探しました。
and then at some point I thought, do I really need this? I already have 30,000
そしてある時、私は「本当にこれが必要なのか？もう3万冊も本があるのに」と思いました。
books, no time to read them, but in fact I still felt the need, and so
本があるのに時間もない。でも実際には必要でした。だから、
to tell myself, 'hold on,' and then I started to observe, and so it is this notion that
「ああ」と思って観察し始めました。そして、私が提案するこの概念は、
I'm going to propose to you, it's to learn here, it's to learn to observe yourselves,
ここで学ぶことです。それは自分自身を観察することを学ぶことです。
to learn to observe your behaviors, in light of these behaviors.
これらの行動の観点から、自分の行動を観察することを学ぶことです。
So, these three things are important, this spiritual notion is fundamental.
したがって、これら3つのことは重要であり、この精神的な概念は根本的です。
This spiritual notion, it's in the sense that we must, we have this role
この精神的な概念は、私たちがこの役割を担っているという意味です。
to learn
学ぶこと。
to teach others.
他の人に教えるために。
perhaps another form of pleasure than just the pleasures of our senses.
私たちの感覚的な喜びだけでなく、別の形の喜びかもしれません。
I believe this is part of this journey.
それがこのトーナメントの一部だと思います。
So consider for a few days, if you have the opportunity,
だから、数日間、もし機会があれば、それを考えてみてください。
that you are as vast as the Earth.
あなたが地球と同じくらい大きいと。
But would you throw
しかし、あなたは紙を捨てるでしょうか？
litter?
紙を？
Anyway, you see, now it's better, but we all have behaviors, all have states.
ほら、今は良くなりましたが、私たちは皆、行動や状態を持っています。
you will see that if you consider that
もしあなたがそれを考慮するなら、
you will start to have a kind of
あなたは一種の、
Indeed, consider this.
ほら、
I will consider myself.
私は自分自身を考慮します。
Thus, we will elevate your practice.
だから、私たちはあなたのゲームを向上させます。
Thus, I will greatly empower you.
だから、私はあなたに巨大なエゴを与えます。
You will be as expansive as the Earth.
あなたは地球と同じくらい大きくなります。
for a few days, and perhaps longer.
数日間、そしておそらくそれ以上。
To be as vast as the Earth is already significant.
すでに地球は悪くありません。
It is opportune that we commence now.
今出発するのは良いことです。
So, this is somewhat.
だから、これは少し、
The idea also is that.
アイデアも、
it is somewhat.
これは少し、
This is also part of this transition, you know, that we may rediscover pleasure,
これもこの移行の一部です。ほら、私たちが喜びを取り戻せるように。
but elsewhere, in fact, by daring to relinquish some of our pleasures,
しかし、別の場所で、実際には、私たちの喜びの一部をあえて手放すことによって。
you know, by perhaps replacing them with something else, such as
ほら、それらを何か別のものに置き換えることによって、例えば、
discovering the pleasure of simplicity.
シンプルさの喜びを発見すること。
You have already experienced this, a pleasure of simplicity.
あなたはすでにそれを経験しましたか？シンプルさの喜びを。
The pleasure of an...
あるものの喜び...
Authentic presence.
本物の存在。
The pleasure that can arise from the relationship
関係から来る喜び。
to things,
物事へ。
rather than the possession of things.
物事を所有するのではなく。
The pleasure of the relationship to things,
物事との関係の喜び。
rather than the pleasure of possession.
所有の喜びではなく。
Because we believe we possess something; no.
なぜなら、私たちは何かを所有していると信じているからです。いいえ。
In fact, we do not possess.
実際には、私たちは所有していません。
The pleasure of contentment.
満足の喜び。
These are subtle elements that emerge from a certain neutrality.
それは、ある種のニュートラルさから来る小さなことです。
Thus, the joy of renunciation.
さて、放棄の喜び。
Initially, when one reads such Buddhist texts, you know, the Buddha stated, at first,
最初、仏教のようなテキストを読むと、ほら、ブッダは言いました、最初は、
my heart was vexed by the necessity of renunciation.
私の心は、放棄しなければならないことに怒っていました。
And now that I have the...
そして今、私がそれを手に入れたので...
experience, I leap with joy into this release. My heart leaps with joy
経験しました。この安堵の中で、私は喜びで跳ね上がります。私の心は喜びで跳ね上がります。
to be able to relinquish
手放すことができること
certain things. So, I suggest to you
あることを。そこで、私はあなたに提案します。
to reflect in this manner. What could you
そのように考えてみてください。あなたは何を
abandon that actually adds suffering to you? There
手放すことができますか？それは実際にはあなたに苦しみを追加しているものです。
are things like that
私の行動には、そのようなものがあります。苦しみを追加しているものを、私は何を捨てることができますか？
that add suffering to my life, or even to others.
私の人生に、あるいは他の人々に苦しみを追加しているものを。
And so I think that, I tell you, as a therapist,
だから、セラピストとして、私はあなたに言います。
we perhaps also have this role, in a certain way, of opening this
私たちには、ある意味で、この意識を開く役割もあるかもしれません。
awareness
意識
that we will have to shift a bit towards that level,
私たちは、このレベルに少し移行しなければならないでしょう。
and perhaps rediscover a bit of simplicity.
そして、おそらく少しのシンプルさを取り戻すでしょう。
I am someone who meditates a lot and often goes on retreats, very simple ones, very
私は瞑想をよくする人で、非常にシンプルなリトリートによく参加します。
simple retreats.
非常にシンプルなリトリートです。
And so I have discovered sometimes, from time to time, my mind, naturally, it
そして、時々、私の心は自然にさまようことが多いのですが、同時に、私は時々、このシンプルさの喜びを発見しました。
wanders a lot, but at the same time, I have sometimes discovered this
さまようことが多いのですが、同時に、私は時々、この
pleasure of this simplicity,
シンプルさの喜びを
of simply being present to my breath, of simply being present to small things like that which are
ただ自分の呼吸に存在すること、ただそこにある小さなものに存在すること。
there.
そこにある。
that means that at some point
それは、ある時点で
you will almost have a joy
あなたはほとんど喜びを感じるでしょう
in losing
失うことの
some of your privileges
あなたの特権の一部を
if that becomes a joy, it will be good
それが喜びになれば、それは良いことです
that was a little bit
これは少し
the perspective, the introduction
見方、導入でした
I wrote that yesterday
昨日これを書きました
that was a little bit
それは少し
the concept
アイデアでした
that we can somewhat broaden our perspective
私たちは視野を少し広げることができます
that we can slightly modify
私たちは少し変えることができます
This is somewhat
それは少し
the work
仕事です
into which we will be guided
私たちが導かれることになる
it is a novel perspective
それは新しい見方です
perhaps a new understanding of phenomena
おそらく物事の新しいビジョンです
This is now
それは今です